donorschoose.org 2018-06-10

# Privacy Policy

#### Last Updated on May 22, 2018

At DonorsChoose.org, we are committed to protecting the privacy of our users. We updated our Privacy Policy on May 22, 2018 to clarify the intended audience of our site, and how we use the information you share with us to help improve your site experience. 

### About DonorsChoose.org

DonorsChoose.org is an online charity that engages the public in public schools by giving people a simple, accountable and personal way to address educational inequity. We envision a nation where children in every community have the tools and experiences needed for an excellent education. Our website is intended for teachers and donors who are United States residents.

### Privacy Principles

Transparency is one of our core values here at DonorsChoose.org. With that in mind, we have developed a privacy policy (this "Privacy Policy") that details how we collect, protect, disclose, and use the information our users provide through their use of the website (www.donorschoose.org), application programming interface (our "API") other sites owned and operated by DonorsChoose.org, and through any direct giving apart from the sites above.

Our Privacy Policy is guided by our core values:

  * **Relentlessness:** We take your privacy seriously and will make our best efforts to protect your personal information.
  * **User focus:** We will never sell your personal information. As a nonprofit organization, we work for our mission, not a profit.
  * **Ingenuity:** The information we collect is used to provide the best experience for teachers, donors and ultimately students, and to find new ways that help us provide you with a delightful experience.
  * **Flexibility:** We make sure to give you access to and control over your information, providing options that best meet your needs.
  * **Transparency:** We service several types of users, so we strive to create a policy that is appropriate and understandable for each customer. If you have any questions about our policy, don't hesitate to contact us at privacy@donorschoose.org.
  * **Teamwork:** Our website is intended for users over the age of 18, but because we serve PreK-12 classrooms, we team up with teachers to help them ensure that their students' personal information is protected. 

### Collection and Use of Your Information

**Information we collect directly from you:** We ask for different personal information depending on how you interact with our website, and will only share it in the instances outlined below. We will **never** sell your information and take measures to protect it from misuse. We currently identify our users as either of the two categories:

  * **Donors:** Users over 18 years of age (according to our Terms of Use) who have made a donation to a project, purchased a gift card or account credits, redeemed a gift card, given directly to the organization, or shared personal contact information as a non-teacher user.
  * **Teachers:** Full-time PreK-12 public school teachers who have set up a teacher account to post projects on our website. All teacher accounts are created with a corresponding donor account.

Listed below are the ways we use the information provided by each user type:

### Donors

Information you provide | How this information is used  
---|---  
Full name & email address | _Required._ We use this information to correspond with you regarding transactional activity, which may include confirmation emails, receipts, acknowledgment messages, and updates on projects you have funded. We will also send you recommendations for projects to support according to your indicated interests, from which you can unsubscribe through your account.   
Payment information | We use the payment information you entered (including billing zip code) in order to process the transaction you authorized, which may be a donation to a project or giving page, purchase of a gift card or account credits, or a monthly donation you previously authorized. You may also choose to save your credit card for future use.

All credit card information is tokenized, including for those users that choose to save their payment information for future use, so your credit card number is never processed or stored on our servers.  
  
Mailing address | _Optional._ For donations over $50, you can opt in to receive thank-you notes from the classroom you supported. We will never sell or give away your mailing address to third parties, share it with the teacher you support or solicit donations using your mailing address.  
Birthday | _Optional._ We'll wish you a happy birthday :)  
  
### Teachers

Information you provide | How this information is used  
---|---  
Full name & email address | _Required._ We use this information to correspond with you regarding your project(s) and use of our website, deliver a monthly teacher newsletter and contact you about special funding opportunities. We need your full name to make sure we can address any material deliveries to the correct teacher.   
Phone number | _Required._ When we are not able to reach you by email, we will use your phone number to contact you about actions required for your project, or funding opportunities in your area.   
School name & grade level | _Required._ We use this to identify the classroom that will benefit from your projects on our website and API.   
Professional/campaign affiliations | _Optional._ We will display professional affiliations on the public project page. This information is used to opt teachers into specific funding opportunities.  
Birthday | _Optional._ We'll wish you a happy birthday :)  
  
### Information that we automatically collect during your visit to our website

Our web server automatically recognizes and collects the domain name and IP address of visitors to our website, and we use cookies to track the pages you've visited on our website. This allows us to provide visitors to our website with certain conveniences, such as delivering projects specific to your location, or pre-populate user information during checkout. We also use cookies to track the path of users through our website, and to keep track of how they arrived at our website (for example, via a search engine). We also collect aggregate tracking information derived mainly from tallying page views throughout our website, and we use Google Analytics Demographics and Interest Reporting to access third-party audience data such as age, gender and interests on an aggregate basis. Finally, we may use third-party analytics tools to track how visitors use our site. This information helps us prevent fraud, troubleshoot problems, and see how users respond to new features. This tracking does not record sensitive information like passwords or credit card data

### How we protect your information

Your privacy is important to us, and we use technical safeguards designed to preserve the security of your personal information and protect it from unauthorized use or disclosure. We understand, however that no system is perfect, and we cannot ensure or warrant the security of any or all of the personal Information you transmit through our website. 

DonorsChoose.org employees, volunteers, interns and contractors ("agents") must have a legitimate business reason (i.e., related directly to furthering our mission) to access personal information you provide. Following the industry's best practices, agents must log in using two-factor authentication and we take steps to limit the amount of access to the minimum level needed to achieve each agent's purpose.

### How we share, publish and transfer your information

We do not sell, trade, or share your personal information to or with others without your explicit consent except: 

  * To respond to your requests or questions;
  * With third parties who perform services on our behalf, for example, with our vendors or payment processors. We may also share information with companies that operate our websites or provide analytics services to show us how users are using our website;
  * If we think we have to in order to comply with the law or to protect ourselves; or
  * With any successor to all or part of our business. For example, in the event of a merger, acquisition, divestiture, change of control or liquidation of DonorsChoose or part of its business (or in anticipation of such an event) we may share that information as part of that transaction. 

We indicate in your account profile which portion of the information you provide will be made public, and offer options for you to control how much information is disclosed. In cases where we share your information with third parties (for example, an employer or website analytics service provider), our Privacy Policy does not govern the privacy practices of such third parties and we ask that you refer to their respective privacy policies for details on their use of your information. 

We also share some information about donors or teachers who participate in specific programs or who use specific features of our website as listed below.

### Donors:

**Donations to a project or teacher page:** We will display your salutation and any user-generated comments publicly on the project page, available on the website and through our API. The teacher you supported will also see your preferred salutation and donation amount in his/her account.

**Gift cards sponsored by corporate partners:** When you use a DonorsChoose.org gift card that was funded by a corporate partner, we may share your name, email address and gift code with the corporate partner that issued the gift card. Our Privacy Policy does not govern the practices of our corporate partners; please refer to the privacy policies of respective corporate partners when using a company-issued gift card.

**Giving pages:** When you make a donation through a Giving Page, in support of a named person or special campaign (for example, contributing funds in support of someone's birthday, wedding, anniversary, 10K run, mustache growing, blog, or any other event), your full name and donation amount will be shared with the creator of that Giving Page.

**Donations matched by a promo code or match offer:** When you support a project that has a match offer (for example, a "Double-Your-Impact" or "Almost Home") or when using a promo code sponsored by a corporate partner, we may share your salutation and donation amount with the corporate partner.

**Employee matching:** We may disclose your contact information (name, postal address, email address and telephone number) and donation information (donation amount and supported projects) to your employer if you have notified us that your employer will match your donation. We are not responsible for the privacy practices of your employer. For more information regarding the handling of your information by your employer, please refer to your employer's privacy policies.

**Think It Up:** If you access our website through ThinkItUp.org and place a donation in support of a Student-led Project, we will share your full name and email address with the Entertainment Industry Foundation (the "EIF"). Our Privacy Policy does not govern the practices of the EIF; please refer to EIF's policy for details on how your information may be used by them.

### Teachers:

**Donors and site visitors:** We will display your title (for example, Ms. and Mr.), last name, school information, professional affiliations, teaching details, and information about your projects (including essays and Thank-you package components) publicly on the site, through our API and in emails sent to donors.

**Verification of affiliation and eligibility:** If you indicate in your account profile that you are a part of any professional affiliations (for example, Teach for America, NEA or New York Teaching Fellow), we may share your full name, email address and phone number with the partner organization or another member of the organization in order to verify your affiliation. These partners are only authorized to use this information for the purpose of verification.

Similarly, we may share your full name, email address and project information with your school administrators or colleagues to confirm that you are eligible to use DonorsChoose.org or take part in certain funding opportunities.

**School officials and colleagues:** When we purchase materials for a fully funded project, we send a fax to your school and an email to your principal and selection of your colleagues who are also teacher users of DonorsChoose.org, sharing your name and a list of funded materials. We may also share project and user information when requested by principals, superintendents, or other employees of local, state, or federal school systems.

**Purchase & fulfillment of projects:**In order to facilitate a seamless fulfillment experience, we'll share your full name, school address and email address with the vendor or service provider you selected when creating your project. Vendors may only use this information to contact you about issues encountered during fulfillment (for example, replacing out-of-stock items, backorder estimates, etc.) or opportunities exclusive to DonorsChoose.org teachers. Vendors or service providers outside of our partner companies (for example, a local museum or special request vendor) do not have a formal relationship with DonorsChoose.org and thus may use your information as outlined in their company's privacy policies.

**Funding opportunities:** If you receive funding through a partner funding opportunity, such as a match offer or full project funding, we may share your full name, school information and project details with the partner company.

**Referrals:** If you participate in one of our referral programs or are referred through one of those programs we may share your account information with a third-party service to verify that the referral is genuine and detect fraudulent referrals.

### Anonymized data sharing

We publish insights gained through user activity on our website (and welcome the public to do the same) in the reports available at data.donorschoose.org. However, we will never publicly disclose your personal information in these reports.

### "Do Not Track" Signals

Some web browsers may transmit "do not track" signals to the websites and other online services with which the browser communicates. There is no standard that governs what, if anything, websites should do when they receive these signals. We currently do not take action in response to these signals. 

### How We Protect Children's Privacy

As an organization that serves students in public school classrooms, we take safety and privacy of children seriously. Our website is not meant to be used by children under the age of 18, unless with explicit parental consent as detailed in our User Agreement.

We do not knowingly collect or solicit information from anyone under the age of 13. In the event that we learn that we have collected personal information from a child under the age of 13 without parental consent, we will delete that information as soon as practicable from our server. If you believe that we might have any information collected from a child under the age of 13, please contact us at privacy(at)donorschoose(dot)org.

Here are the ways in which we work with classroom teachers to ensure the protection of student information:

  * Teacher account photos are vetted by our project screeners to ensure there are no close-up photos of students or personally identifiable information in their photos. Photos of students are optional and require permission from a parent or guardian before being submitted for use on our site.
  * When constructing Thank-You packages, teachers are given photo safety guidelines, which prohibit personally identifiable information and close-up photos of students.
  * Any personally identifiable information included in thank-you notes from students (for example, full name, email address or phone number) is removed by our team before being sent to donors.
  * Teachers who create a Student-led Project are required to ensure that all students taking part in the project are over the age of 13. These students may share their first name and contact information, the latter only for internal use by DonorsChoose.org.

### How You Can Access and Adjust Your Information

You may correct your account information at any time by logging into your online account. You have the right to request access to the personal information that we record about you. You also have the right to request corrections, amendments and deletions of any of your personal information in our possession. To make these changes or cancel your account, please email us at privacy

### Updates to Our Privacy Policy

DonorsChoose.org may modify this Privacy Policy from time to time. When changes are made, DonorsChoose.org will indicate the modification change date in the "last updated" date at the top of the page. If we make any material changes to the policy, we will notify you in an email (sent to the email specified in your account profile) or in a notification on our website. We encourage you to periodically review this Privacy Policy to be informed of how DonorsChoose.org is protecting your information. Your continued use of our website after a modification of our Privacy Policy indicates your consent to such modification.

### How to contact DonorsChoose.org

We are always happy to hear from you with your questions or comments! For additional information, or if you have any questions regarding this Privacy Policy or our privacy practices in general, please send your questions or comments to us at privacy@donorschoose.org. You can also send questions or comments to the address below.

DonorsChoose.org   
Attn: Trust & Safety   
134 West 37th Street  
11th Floor  
New York, NY 10018
